Guide to the International Monitor Institute. Rwanda Videotapes and Audiotapes, 1992-1999 RL.00607
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Rwanda Videotapes Series, 1992-1999, 5 boxes
  - Radio Télévision Libre des Mille Collines (RTLM) Investigation, February Meeting 1994, VHS [TRT 00:06:40] (Box 374, Video-cassette RW046)
    Air Date: 1997 July 28
    Producer: Unknown
    Meeting that gathered the Minister of Information who expressed his concern about the objectivity of RTLM and the president of RTLM, the shareholders included F. Nahimana. They share the same argument that RTLM is an independent radio concerned with reporting news the way it occurs.
    - Digital preservation and use files (Digital-materials RL00607-SET-0002, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW046.mov, Video-file RL00607-VHS-RW046.mp4)
  - Bout à Bout, Rwanda, PAL SECAM [TRT 00:28:27] (Box 374, Video-cassette RW047)
    Air Date: 1996 Oct. 25
    Producer: TF1
    "This tape runs for about 20 minutes. Nahida Nakad of TF1 did the reporting between April and July 1994.
    1. First item shows the St. Jean church in Kibuye. Services were still being held despite the sight and smell of decomposing bodies scattered around church grounds. A priest was asked about the smell. He responded that "people are getting used to it."
    Images of Tutsi hiding in the hills out of fear of Hutu attacks.
    2. Goma in the evening. Surgeons operate on wounded and mutilated children. They were the victims of machete attacks.
    Several survivors offer their testimony. Some Tutsi hid in the forests.
    3. 94 Tutsi, survivors of various attacks, arrive in Goma. Most of them are young as the old were too fragile to survive their extensive wounds. Alphonsine, a ten year-old girl, is interviewed.
    4. Helicopters of the French army evacuate about 40 nuns. A nun is asked whether they feared for their lives. She responds that "on était sur le qui-vive."
    A French army officer is interviewed.
    5. French soldiers bring jean-Baptiste, a Tutsi survivor, to Kibuye stadium. This was the site of yet another massacre. Jean-Baptiste gives a moving account of the events that took place within the stadium.
    6. Reporters arrive at a mission where a number of nuns from St. Marie have taken refuge. One nun maintains that local authorities attempted to protect the nuns from attacks.
    7. Reporter comes across several members of the interim government at the Meridien hotel in Gisenyi, a few kilometers from the border with Zaire. One minister proclaims that the "massacres have been spontaneously organized by the population. It is a civilian rebellion."
    The minister maintains that there is no militia to speak of. The Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF)'s better equipped but the French presence has served to reassure the government forces.
- Rwanda Audiotapes Series (Audiocassette), 1993-1994, 8 boxes
  - RTLM 1 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW001)
    Air Date: 1994 May 12
    Producer: RTLM
    Original Language: Kinyarwanda, French
    Il faut vérifier que le discours de Kambanda passe en fait à la RTLM.
    Kantano commence l'émission avec un appel aux Rwandais de combattre les "Inyenzi", notamment les enfants de Tutsi qui sont partis en 1959. Il parle ensuite de l'extermination imminente des Tutsi dans "le monde entier." Kantano demande aussi que le peuple Rwandais fasse attention à sa réputation internationale et participe à la guerre sans se permettre de piller et tuer n'importe comment. Il termine la face a en soulignant l'importance de la RTLM. La face B est composée entièrement d'un discours du Premier Ministre Jean Kambanda. Il adresse le peuple Rwandais et explique la formation et les objectifs du nouveau gouvernement. Kambanda accuse le FPR d'avoir assassiné le Président Habyarimana et il incite la population à se réunir pour combattre les "Inyenzi" et les enfants de Tutsi qui ont quitté le pays en 1959. Il ne laisse aucun doute qu'il s'agit d'un problème entre les ethnies et que le FPR est composé de Tutsi.
  - RTLM 2, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 126, Audio-cassette RW002)
    Air Date: 1994 May 16-17
    Unidentified speaker begins by suggesting Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) has massacred 8000 Hutus with the consent of the UN. Georges Ruggiu and unidentified journalist enjoin people in Kigali not to let journalist get interviews or images of their activities, which are apparently compromising.
    Kantano previews upcoming interview with a 12 year old RPF soldier. The boy will reveal the RPF's use of collaboration with 'sorcerers' and 'women who suck themselves' and Inkotanyi plans for a massacre in Nyamirambo that will start with the killing of a man called Abdou.
    Kantano (1) calls for vigilance at the barriers; (2) tells listeners to watch their neighbors' reaction to the upcoming taped interview, and arrest those neighbors that seem concerned by what the child is saying; (3) calls for the arrest of other Inkotanyi street children bearing a certain mark on their scalp; (4) for an attack to kill Inkotanyi living in huts near Rugunga before they listen to RTLM and flee; (4) for the "arrest" of three specific street children at Kimisagara as well as 30 others. Kantano says the interviewed child should be kept alive.
    In an interview with journalists Biziyaremye Thimothe and Kayitare Vianney, the RPF boy soldier claims to have spied on the barriers with other boys bearing grenades, kalachnikovs and pistols. Under interrogation, the boy gives the location of his fellow Inkotanyi: (1) at Gitega on the macadamized road, (2) at Kiyovu, "in front of the houses of whites who keep horses," (3) at Gatenga, (4) "at the marsh near road to Gikongo," (5) at Butamwa, (6) at Byumba, (7) at Jari, (8) at Rebero. Child provides names of family members, reveals that soldiers travel by foot and work with sorcerers and gives specific information about vehicles and weapons used by his fellow Inkotanyi. Interview ends with account of how he and other boys set up booby trap mines to kill Hutu.
    Kantano launches another monologue in which: (1) Belgian are called 'sons-of bitches" who car only for women and money, (2) Inkotanyi are described as wild animals that "hunt moles, partridges and cicadas, (3) a prophesy is made that "Inkotanyi will die in our potatoes', (4) FAR soldiers are encouraged to remain in good spirits,(4) the invaders are described as dogs that must be killed before they kill, (5) citizens are encouraged to help FAR soldiers or be taken prisoner by the Inkotanyi, (6) a letter is read from a listener telling of collaboration between the Ugandans, the Belgians, and the "cockroaches." These "cockroaches" (no discrimination made between soldiers and civilians) are being hunted down and killed by FAR soldiers, and this will continue until they accept negotiations.
    Side A concludes with personal missives from and to active soldiers. (Side B is blank)
    Tape includes strong evidence: direct calls, ethnic slurs, anti-Belgian rhetoric. Suggestion that captured RPF soldiers must reveal name of family members.
    Need voice analysis to confirm that the journalist "George is in fact George Ruggiu.
    Side B of tape is blank.
    Emission highlights a taped interview with captured RPF boy soldier who reveals location of alleged Inkotanyi collaborators in numerous specific locations. Kantano calls for killing of people living in specific huts as well as for the arrest of RPF street children.
  - Gahigi-Amanie, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 119, Audio-cassette RW003)
    Air Date: 1994 May 14
    No description available.
  - RTLM 4, Sony HF 60 (Box 119, Audio-cassette RW004)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr. 12
    The tape begins with discussion by Simbizi, Bemericki, Bamwanga, and Karamira regarding the objectives sought and roles played by various political parties including the RPF, CDR, and MDR. Bamwanga then announces that no one has fled Kigali and urges listeners to remain on night patrols and on the barriers.
    Kantano then begins a long monologue which runs through the end of side A. The monologue goes as follows: (1) Rwandans are united in fighting the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) and foreigners cannot come in and steal what the Rwandans have built; (2) a direct call against four Tutsi in the Kimisagara and Nyakanda area; (3) a call to vigilance on the barriers; (3) a report of Tutsis being shot in Remera and a justification of this on the grounds that Tutsis have encircled and killed people; (4) a report that Tutsis are using people as shields; they are thieves and they kill Hutus with machetes; (5) an attack on Twagiramungu, Kanyarenwe, and Pasteur Bizimungu and an expression of appreciation that Rwandans continue to work together; (6) a warning that Tutsis will track Hutus down and kill them; (7) the Tutsis have lied about taking certain regions; (8) criticisms of the UN.
    Side B continues with Kantano's monologue. He states that the transition government is strong and that the Rwandans are recruiting young boys and girls into the army, waiting with machetes to kill the cockroaches. The Tutsis are in Arusha using Ibizungerezi (attractive Tutsi women) to mislead people. RTLM was bombed and broadcasters were injured but the station will continue to broadcast.
    Ruggiu replaces Kantano. He indicates the cockroaches are malicious and attacks Twagiramungu. He then speaks about Rwandan history with respect to the Tutsi superiority complex and feudalist aspirations.
    Gahigi replaces Ruggiu and speaks of Rwandan delegations going abroad to promote the cause of Rwandan government. He states the delegations will explain that Habyarimana was killed by the RPF, which (1) wanted to take power by force, (2) annulled the Arusha Peace Accords, and (3) has killed innocent people.
    Tape contains some strong evidence: direct call, strong accusations of Tutsi atrocities, anti-Belgian statements
    Tape labeled April 12, 1994, but in broadcast, date given as April 22 or 23, 1994 (see records 1 and 5); April 22 appears to be correct date.
    Need to confirm that "Karamira" is "Frodauld Karamira"
    Tape begins with a round table discussion on politics among Simbizi, Bemericki, Bamwanga, and Karamira. Kantano then launches a long monologue in which he accuses the RPF of committing atrocities, justifies killing "cockroaches," and makes a direct call against suspected "cockroaches'. Ruggiu then recalls the historical oppression of Hutus by Tutsis in past centuries and under colonialism. Gahigi ends the broadcast by summarizing how the Rwandan government is explaining the current events to the world.
  - RTLM 4, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 119, Audio-cassette RW005)
    Air Date: 1994 May 15
  - RTLM, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 119, Audio-cassette RW006)
  - RTLM 5, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 119, Audio-cassette RW007)
    Cette cassette contient des émissions datant du 15 Mai 1994 aussi bien que du 16 Mai.
    La face A de la cassette, animée par Gaspard Gahigi, est très courte. Gahigi lance un appel aux les citoyens Rwandais de joindre la FAR dans sa bataille contre les envahisseurs arrogants, de rester vigilants, et de montrer du courage aux barrières. Il raconte qu'un radio émetteur a été saisi d'un Inkotanyi à Munanira, Nyakabanda, et que les citoyens doivent "dénicher l'ennemi partout où il se cache pour qu'ils sachent que nous sommes vigilants." La face B de la cassette est animée par Kantano et Ananie. Kantano critique les hommes politiques hutus d'avoir attendu l'assassinat du président pour commencer leurs discours anti-Tutsi. Puis Ananie fait un rapport sur un nombre de complots couvés par les Tutsi pour conquérir le Rwanda ou le repartitioner pour en créer un pays tutsi. Ananie reprends le microphone et accuse le FPR d'avoir commis des atrocités contre des Hutu (au Stade Amahoro et à l'hôpital Roi Faycal), et suggère aussi qu'il y a des groupes de faux Interahamwe qui ont de fausses listes. Kantano continue; il dit que la tuerie ne doit pas continuer sans discrimination, que les Tutsi qui sont toujours vivants sont peut-être innocents, et que "les jolies femme [tutsi]" ne doivent pas être tuées simplement pour plaire aux jaloux femmes hutus. Puis, Kantano dit aux auditeurs qu'ils doivent "encercler," et "stopper" ces "kamikaze" tutsi.
  - RTLM 5, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 119, Audio-cassette RW008)
    Air Date: 1994 Apr. 22
    Producer: Radio Rwanda
    La date de transmission est incertaine; l'attestation provisoire de trascription donne la date de 17 Mai "1974"; la liste de ICTR donne la date de 17 Mai, 1994.
    Cette transcription semble être le même que le numèro 115 (en Englais)
    Face B commence avec un monologue d'un animateur non-identifié (peut-être Simbizi)
    La face A de la cassette est animée par Georges Ruggiu et Valérie Bemeriki. Pendant l'émission, les animateurs répètent que les Accords d'Arusha sont des accords de guerre, et non de paix, une ruse des "Inyenzi-inkotanyi" pour assujetir la majorité et revenir aux temps des massacres et de la domination Tutsi [avant '59]. Le FPR et Twagiramgu sont à plusieurs reprises accusés du meurtre de Habyarimana: Bemeriki appellent aux citoyen de réagir contre les tueurs comme on réagirait contre les tueurs de son propre père; Ruggiu appelle aux citoyen de prêter main forte à la FAR et d'aider à "netoyer" Kigali et tout le pays des "Inyenzi" — comme le FAR viens de faire sur la colline de Rebero. Les Belges sont aussi critiqués et accusés d'être les perroquet du FPR.
    Sur la face B de la cassette, Kantano et Bemeriki dirigent un entretien avec Simbizi (CND) et Froduald Karamira (MDR). Pendant la discussion, un premier animateur accuse les Belges d'une longue liste d'injustices et crimes contre "la majorité." Puis Karamira et Simbizi appellent à la population de s'unir avec l'armée et d'aider à decouvrir tout ennemi qui essaye de se cacher (dans la canalisation, dans les buissons, dans les bananaraies). Les animateurs accusent les Tutsis d'avoir essayé de retourner à la domination économique et politique qu'ils occupaient avant 1959. Les animateurs ajoutent que les Tutsis ont provoqué leurs propre morts. Le FPR est aussi accusé d'avoir tué des Hutu important et d'avoir commis des massacres contre la population.
  - RTLM 6, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 119, Audio-cassette RW009)
    Air Date: 1994 May 18
    -la face B est vierge
    Ananie commence la face A en déclarant que chaque jour mille réfugiés traversent la frontière pour s'échapper des "Inyenzi." Il souhaite que ces réfugiés s'organisent à la frontière pour qu'ils puissent revenir au Rwanda et participer à la guerre contre les "Inyenzi." Ananie se lance ensuite dans une tirade contre Museveni et les Américains qu'il accuse de soutenir les Tutsi dans leur but d'exterminer les Hutu. Kantano le suit dans un entretien avec Bugingo qui se trouve souvent aux barrières. Ce dernier rapporte que la sécurité à Kigali s'améliore et que la population participe aux rondes nocturnes. Il annonce que les Interahamwe ont du succès dans leur chassent à l'Inkotanyi. Par contre, il déclare que la population ne doit pas utiliser sa position aux barrières, ni le fait d'avoir un fusil, comme prétexte pour voler. Bugingo ajoute que des patrouilles ont été formés pour fouiller les maisons soupçonnées de héberger des "Inyenzi." Kantano continue unmonologue sans Bugingo. Kantano se moque d'abord de Kagame qui a promis de passer la nuit à Kigali. Il annonce ensuuite que les Français vont envoyer des troupes au Rwanda. Il demande alors à la population de ne plus s'entre tuer et ignorer la justice. Il termine l'émission en déclarant que des femmes sorcières sont en train de brûler à Rebero et que la communauté internationale a finalement compris que les "Inyenzi" tuent les gens en les torturant.
  - RTLM 8, Sony Super EF 90 (Box 119, Audio-cassette RW010)
    Air Date: 1994 May 21
    La cassette commence avec un dialogue entre Gahigi et Nemeye Ephrem à propos de "ce problème d'éthnicité" à partir duquel les "Inkotanyis" sont accusés d'avoir commis des massacres, tué le président, commencé la guerre, et negocié les Accords d'Arusha. Puis, Gahigi entretiens Claire Kayirange, une fille qui "travaille" à la barrière de Muhima. Elle est louée comme un example pour les autres filles qui doivent, elles-aussi, prendre des armes contre "les petits Inyenzis" et faire "la ronde nocturne." Après une intervention de Nkomati, et un autre d'un animateur francophone non identifié entretiens deux refugiés hutus: Epimaque Abiyingoma (assistant bourgmestre de la commune de Rutare) et Cyriagque Habiyambere. Les deux hommes temoignent sur des nombreuses attrocités commis par les "Inkotanyis" contre la population non tutsi.
  - RTLM 11, Sony HF 60 (Box 119, Audio-cassette RW011)
    Air Date: 1994 May 28
  - RTLM 12, Sony HF 60 (Box 119, Audio-cassette RW012)
    Kantano is the only speaker on side A of this transcript. Among other things Kantano addresses the refugee problem. He alternately pleads with his listeners to resist fleeing and berates them for leaving. He insists that the Inkotanyi present very little threat to the lives of Rwandans if only the population stays put. Kantano explains that the Inkotanyi use "whirlwind tactics" to hide their small numbers and to scare the Rwandan population into taking flight. In a rage, he calls on people at the check points to check refugees who have left with all their belongings. He refers to them as cowards. Kantano also adresses the Inkotanyi and warns them that they will "be a party without adherents," that no one will be left in half of the communes they have conquered if they do not stop their invasion. He informs them that Rwandans will never allow the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) to rule over them and he urges the population to take up arms against the "Inyenzi." Finally, Kantano also emphasizes that Kigali is not yet in the hands of the "Inyenzi" regardless of all the rumors and misinformation.
    Apart from Ananie's brief discussion of the foreign press and his quip that "Kigali has been captured, it has been captured by RFI, the BBC and Radio Muhabura," side B is devoted to Gahigi' interviews with people at various check points throughout Kigali. Gahigi speaks with children, CDR militants, FAR soldiers, militants at the road blocks and several civilians. The interviews give evidence that Kigali is in no danger of falling to the Inkotanyi and that many "Inyenzi" have been killed.
  - RTLM 13, Sony HF 60 (Box 119, Audio-cassette RW013)
  - RTLM 13, Sony HF 60 (Box 119, Audio-cassette RW014)
    Air Date: 1994 May 29
    Transcript begins mid-sentence with unidentified speaker urging listeners to come "work with RTLM." Those who do not understand that "this war... is the final one" and so cannot work "there" [reference is possibly to roadblocks] should be kept away and appointed to "non-confidential and unimportant cases," such as "checking vehicles that have broken down."
    After an interruption, transcript begins with Kantano interviewing a Kimicanga resident who claims to have killed 5 Inyenzi thieves in Magerwa. Kantano congratulates the resident, who he calls "Caporal," and asks that he "keep it up." The resident then urges "soldiers in Kicukiro" to also "keep it up," and specifically names their precise locations. Kantano and interviewee suggest that soldiers are working with residents in Magerwa, and perhaps other places, where Inyenzi were killed. The residents suggests that contrary to reports, the FAR still controls Kimicanga, Kacyiru, Magerwa, Kicukiro.
    Another resident then speaks on behalf of RTLM. Kantano urges this resident and others to "test" people's knowledge of the station and its broadcasters. Residents standing close by respond by pronouncing the names of their favorite announcers.
    Another resident in the crowd, a member of the CDR and of the Kimicanga security committee, says he is a peasant, part of the "mass who is at the barriers" and which often listens to RTLM. He says his militia is "keeping it up" at Kimicanga, Kajevuba, and Rwintare. He says roadblocks should be more lax for the "sons of Sebahinzi," (i.e. Hutu peasants), but that those who do not have papers showing that they are "sons of Sebahinzi" should "leave their head there" at the roadblock.
    A soldier then takes the microphone and warns that Inkotanyi chased out of Kanombe "will be beaten for a long time" if they come there to Kimicanga. Kantano once again says "keep it up."
    After a Bikindi song, Ananie transmits a few missives to and from soldiers.
    Gahigi then begins a circuitous monologue about how the government should deal with the refugees in Mille Collines Hotel and Amahoro Stadium and ensure their security.
    After another musical interlude, an unidentified speaker (1) criticizes false RFI reports about Kigali's fall, (2) speaks of plans to "evacuate people... in Mille Collines Hotel and Amahoro Stadium, (3) discusses common international misunderstanding about what the Rwandan Patriotic Front (RPF) is doing and "who is [really] massacring who," (4) alleges governments supporting the arms embargo bear responsibility for RPF massacre of civilian population, (5) accuses Beligian mercenaries of collaboration with RPF in massacre of Hutus, (6) denies that militias of presidential guards were involved in massacres, saying that at time of massacres, there was no government, (7) alleges that assassination of Habyarimana and other top Rwandan officials marked beginning of RPF's massacring plans.
    Broadcast ends with criticism of U.S. participation in arming of UN troops in Rwanda.
    Very strong evidence of RTLM collaboration with militias.
    Date discrepancy: tape label reads 29 May, but one speaker in program says "yesterday on the 26th of May 94"
    Side B is blank
    Tape features Kantano interview with residents and soldier at the Kimikanga roadblock. Announcers also discuss situation at Mille Colline Hotel and allege Tutsi atrocities.
  - RTLM 14, Sony HF 60 (Box 119, Audio-cassette RW015)
    Les deux face de la cassette sont animées par Kantano. Il félicite la FAR pour son détournement d'un massacre qui, il dit, allait être perpétué par les Inkotanyi contre la population de Kicukiro. Pendant le reste de l'émission, trois thèmes sont abordés à plusieurs reprises: (1) le plan des Inkotanyi de massacrer tout les Hutus, (2) le fait que le Rwandais doivent avoir du courage pour "travailler" contre ceux qui viennent les tuer et prendre leurs biens, (3) une critique de Radio Muhabura et une accusation qu'elle aide à verser le sang des Hutus, (4) la population et l'armée sont encouragées de fumer du chanvre "pour affronter efficacement ces voyous qui ont envahis nos champs en vue de voler nos récoltes." Kantano conclue la face B avec la caution que, "ils (les Inkotanyis) ont tout intérêt à arrêter les combats car si ils continuent à se suicider, ils seront tous éliminés."
  - RTLM 15, Sony HF 60 (Box 119, Audio-cassette RW016)
    Air Date: 1994 May 30
    Le début de la cassette est coupé.
    La face A de cette cassette contient un long monologue de Kantano. Il commence avec un rapport qui accuse le Inkotanyi d'avoir essayé de s'infiltrer à Nyamirambo, Muhima et Gisozi. Kantano rassure ensuite ses auditeurs que le grondement d'armes lourdes sont ou la manifestation du FAR qui pourchassent les "Inyenzi" ou une stratégie des Inkotanyi pour faire peur aux peuple Rwandais. Kantano continue son monologue avec des exhortations dirigées aux écouteurs de la RTLM. Il les indique que des fusils seront distribués à la population et que si ils se mettent ensemble ils pourront exterminer les "Inyenzi." Kantano accuse aussi les Inkotanyi d'empêcher que des négociations prennent place.